Over the years it became clear that DES
and triple DES are simply not designed for
多年来，DES和三重DES明显不是为硬件来设计的。
modern hardware and are too slow. As a
result, NIS started a new process to
并且他们速度很慢。于是，NIS建立了一个新的标准化分组密码程序，
standardize in a new block cypher called
the Advanced Encryption Standard or AES
叫做高级加密标准，简称AES。
for short. Nis started it's effort in 1997
when it requested, proposals for a new
NIS请求了一个新的分组密码建议书并且在1977年开工。
block cipher. It received fifteen
submissions a year later. And finally in
一年后，它一共收到了15份提议。最终在2000年，
the year 2000, it adopted the cypher
called Rijndael the advanced encryption.
它采用了一个叫做Rijndael的高级加密标准
standard. This was a cypher designed in
Belgium. We already said that it's block
这是当时在比利时设计的一套密码。我们要了解的是
size is 128 bits and it has three possible
key sizes. 128 bits, 192, and 256. Now,
它的分组大小是128比特,并且可以有三种大小的密钥，128、192、256比特。
the assumption is that the larger the key
size is, the more secure the block cipher
前提是密钥越长，作为一个为伪随机置换的分组密码安全性就越高。
is as a pseudo random permutation. But
because it also has more rounds involved
但是，由于它同时也包含了更多的操作轮数，
in its operation. The slower the cipher
becomes. So the larger the key supposedly,
使得密码变得更慢。所以，密钥越长，
the more secure the cipher, but also the
slower it becomes. So for example, AES 128
密码就越安全，速度也就越慢。
is the fastest of these ciphers and AES
256 is the slowest. Now AES is built as
例如，AES中128比特的密钥就是最快的而256比特就是最慢的。
what's called a substitution permutation
network. It's not a Feistel network.
现在AES由一种代换-置换网络构建而成。这不是一种 Feistel 网络，
Remember that in a Feistel network, half
the bit were unchanged from round to
记住这个，在Feistel结构中，一半的比特在一轮置换中是不变的。
round. In a substitution permutation
network all the bits are changed in every
而在这种代换-置换网络中，所有的比特在每一轮置换中都会变。
round. And the network works as follows,
so here we have the first round of the
这种网络工作如下，在代换-置换网络中的第一轮，
substitution permutation network, where
the first thing we do is we XOR the
首先我们要做的是用轮密钥来异或初始状态，
current state with the round key. In this
case the first round key. Then we go throught
第一轮的情况下是用第一个轮密钥。然后，
a substitution layer, where blocks of Date
are replaced with other blocks based on
我们经过一个代换层，在这个代换层中，分组数据和代换表中的分组进行替换。
what the substitution table says. And then
we go through a permutation layer where
然后我们进入置换层，在这里比特会被置换移位。
bits are permuted and shuffled around. And
then we do this again. We XR with an X
然后，我们再来一遍，我们用轮密钥异或，
round key, we go thru a substitution
phase, and we're permute to dance around.
再经过代换阶段，然后再置换
And so on, and so on, and so forth Until
we reach the final round where we xor
然后再不厌其烦的进行下去，直到我们到达最后一轮
with the very last around key, and then
out comes the output. Now, and important
并且在用最后一个轮密钥异或以后，就得到输出
point about this design. Is that, in fact,
because of how it's built, every step in
现在这个设计最重要的就是它的结构网络中，
this network needs to be reversible, so
that the whole thing is reversible. And so
每一步都必须是可逆的，才能让整个过程是可逆的。
the way we would, decrypt, essentially, is
we would take the output and simply apply
解密的方式是我们利用输出和应用网络中的每一步来反向解密。
each step of the network in reverse order.
So we start with the permutation step, and
所以我们先从置换开始，
we have to make sure that step is
reversible. Then we look at the
确保这一步都是可逆的。
substitution layer, and we have to make
sure this step is reversible. And this is
然后我们再看下代换层，也必须保证是可逆的。
very different from DES. In DES, if you
remember, the substitution tables were not
而且这个DES非常不同。如果你有印象的话，
reversible at all. In fact, they
map six bits to four bits. Whereas
就应该知道DES中的代换表不是可逆的因为它从6个比特映射成4个比特。
here, everything has to be reversible,
otherwise it would be impossible to
然而在这里，所有的步骤都必须是可逆的，否则不可能解密。
decrypt. And of course the xor with the
round key is reversible as well. Okay? So
当然和轮秘钥异或也要是可逆的才行。明白了没？
inversion of a substitution permutation
network is simply done by applying all of
反向实现代换-置换网络是很容易的，只要把
the steps in the reverse order. So now
that we understand the generic
所有的步骤反过来做一遍就可以了。现在我们理解了它的通用结构
construction. Lets look at the specifics
of AES. So AES operates on a 128 bit block.
让我们来看看AES的一些特征.AES每个分组有128比特，
Which is sixteen bytes. So what we do with
AES is we write those sixteen bytes as a
也就是16字节。所以我们把这16字节写成一个4×4的矩阵。
four by four matrix. Each cell in the
matrix contains one byte. And then we
矩阵中每个单元占一个字节。然后我们
start with the first round so we XOR
with the first round key and then apply a
从第一轮开始，我们用第一个轮密钥异或，然后在用一个确定的函数
certain function. That, includes
substitutions and permutations and other
这个函数包括代换、置换和列混合在里面。
operations on the state. And again, these
three functions that are applied here have
还有一点就是这三个被用到函数都需要是可逆的
to be invertible so that in fact the
cypher can be decrypted. And then we xor
密码才能进行解密。然后我们用，
with the next round key and we do that
again. Again we apply the round function
下一个轮密钥来异或，接着再做一次。再一次使用轮函数
and xor the round key. And we do that
again and again and again. We do it ten
然后再一次进行异或。一直这样进行下去。
times. Although interestingly in the last
round, the mix column step is actually
我们一共这样做10次。有趣的是，在最后一轮中，列混合操作没有了。
missing. And then finally, we XOR with the
last rounds key, and out comes the output.
最后，我们用最后一个轮密钥来异或，然后就输出了结果。
Again, in every phase here, we always,
always, always keep this four by four
并且，在这里的每一个数组，我们总是将它变换成4×4的矩阵。
array. And so the output is also four by
four, which is sixteen bytes, which is 128
所以，最终的输出也总是4×4的矩阵，16字节，128比特。
bits. Now the long key themselves of
course come from a sixteen byte AES key
那么，这些长密钥当然本身是来自16字节的AES秘钥。
using key expansion. So the key expansion
maps from a sixteen bytes AES key
使用秘钥扩展得来的。所以这些来自16字节的AES秘钥密钥映射成11个密钥。
into eleven keys, each one being sixteen
bytes. So these keys themselves are also a
成11个密钥，每个秘钥都是16字节。所以，这些密钥他们和初始状态异或时。
four by four array that's XORed into the
current state. Okay, so that's the
就是4×4的矩阵。这就是AES工作的原理。
schematic of how AES works. And the only
thing that's left to do is specify these
现在唯一剩下的就是把这三个函数列出来，
three functions, byte sub, shift row, and
mixed column. And those are fairly easy to
他们就是字节代换、行移位和列混合。并且很容易将他们解释清楚
explain. So I'm just gonna give you the
high level description of what they are.
那关于它们，我就给你们做一个高层次的描述。
And, those interested in the details can
look it up online. So the way byte
有兴趣的人可以在网上找一些关于它们的细节。
substitution works, is literally it's one
S box containing 256 bytes. And
字节代换，字面上来说，就是一个256字节的代换表（即S-盒）。
essentially, what it does is it applies
the S box to every byte in the current
本质上，它的功能就是对当前状态的每一个字节应用S盒。
states. So, let me explain what I mean by
that. So the current state is gonna be
让我来解释一下。初始状态是一个4×4的表，
this four by four, table. So here we have
the four by four table. And to each
表中的每一个元素都可以应用S-盒。
element in this table, we apply the S box.
So let's call it the A table. And then
我们就叫他表A。然后我们要做的是，
what we do is, essentially, for all four
by four entries, essentially, the next
对所有的4X4的项，下一步，A[i,j].
step, Aij. Becomes the current step
evaluated at the look up table. So we use
就变成这个查阅表中对应的值。
the current cell as an entry, as an index,
into the look up table. And then the value
然后我们用当前的这个单元，作为一个索引，做一个指针，指向查阅表。
of the look up table is what's output.
Okay. So, that's the first step. The next
然后这个表的中的值就是输出。好吧，这就是第一步。
step that happens is a shiftRow step,
which is basically just a permutation. So
接下来就是行移位，它基本上就是一个置换。
essentially we kind of do a stick lick
shift on each one of the rows. So you can
让我们把每一行进行一次循环移位。
see the second row is stick lick shifted
by one position. This third row is
所以我们就看到第二行被移位了一次。
[inaudible] shifted by two positions and
the third row is [inaudible] shifted by
第三行被移了两个位置。第四行被位移了三个位置
three positions. And the last thing we do
is mix columns where literally we apply a
最后一个就是列混合，字面上来看就是
linear transformation to each one of these
columns. So there's a certain matrix that
把每一列进行一次线性变换。这有一个矩阵，
multiplies each one of these columns and
it becomes, the next column. So these
它乘以它中的每一列然后成为下一列。
linear transformation is applied
independently to each one of the columns.
所以这些线性变换是彼此独立的。
Now, I should point out that, so far,
shift rows and mixed columns are very easy
我要指出的是，目前为止，行移位和列混合式是非常简单就能用代码实现的。
to implement in code. And I should say
that the [inaudible] institution itself is
并且字节变换也是很容易计算的，
also easily computable, so that you can
actually write code that takes less than
你甚至用不到256字节就可以写下这些代码
256 bytes to write. And you can kind of
shrink the description of AES by literally
所以你可以缩小AES的描述通过代码计算这个表，
storing code that computes the table
rather than hardwiring the table into your
而不用把他们硬写进代码里实现。
implementation. And in fact, this is kind
of a generic fact about AES, that if you
事实上，这是AES的一个普遍事实吧，
can have allowed no pre computation at
all, including computing the S box on the
如果你不允许用预计算的话，包括即时计算S-盒。
fly. Then in fact you get a fairly small
implementation of AES, so it, it could fit
事实上，你得到一个非常小的AES，
on very constrained environments where
there isn't enough room to hold,
它可以适应没有足够空间储存非常复杂的代码的局限环境
complicated code. But of course, this will
be the slowest implementation, because
不过当然，这肯定会非常慢，
everything is computed now on the fly, and
as a result, the implementation,
因为任何东西都是飞速计算的，所以
obviously, is gonna be, slower than things
that were pre-computed. And then there is
显而易见的，它会比那些可以预计算的要慢。
this trade off. For example if you have a
lot of space, and you can support large
这就是交替使用。例如，你有大量空间，你可以支持大量的代码，
code. You can actually precompute quite a
bit of the three steps that I just
你可以进行很多的预计算，关于刚才那三个步骤。
mentioned. In fact, there are multiple
options of pre-computation, you can build
事实上，有多种预计算方法，你可以构建一个4K字节大的表格
a table that's only four kilobyte big. You
can build a table that is even longer,
你可以构建一个更长的，可以是24K字节。
maybe 24 kilobytes. So basically you will
have these big tables in your
所以，你可以在你的应用里使用这些很大的表格。
implementation. But then your actual
performance is going to be really good,
然后你的实际性能就会非常的好
because all your doing is just table
look-ups and XORs. You're not doing
因为所有你所做的仅仅是查表和异或。
any other complicated arithmetic. And as a
result, if you can do a lot of
你没有做其他任何复杂的算法。所以，你可以做很多预计算
pre-computation, these three steps here,
ByteSub and ShiftRow and MixColumn
我前面说的，字节代换、行移位、列混合
can be converted just into a
number, a small number of table lookups
可以只进行一些少量的查表和一些异或。
and some XOR. All you can do is
just compute the S box, so now your
所有你可以做的计算只需要计算S-盒，
implementation would just have 256 bytes.
Hard coded The rest would just be code
现在你的应用只有256个字节。硬性编码剩下的部分，
that's actually computing these three
functions. The performance would be slower
其实是用来运算这三个函数，最后的结果肯定比
than in the previous step but the code
footprint would also be smaller. So in
先前的要慢得多，即便是代码可能更少
overall, there's this nice tradeoff
between code size and performance. So on
总的来说代码大小和性能之间有一个很好的平衡点
high-end machines, on high-end servers,
where you can afford to have a lot of
在高端机器、服务器上，你可以承受大量代码
code, you can precompute and store these
big tables and get the best performance.
就可以预先计算，把这些打表存到代码里以获得最好的性能。
Whereas on low-end machines like eight
byte smart cards or think of like an eight
然而，一个低档次的机器，例如8比特的智能卡或者一个8比特的手表
byte wristwatch, you would actually have a
relatively small implementation of AES.
如果你有一个相当小的AES
But as a result of course it won't be so
fast. So here's an example that's a little
结果就是它肯定不会很快。这有一个不常用的例子
unusual, suppose you wanted to implement
AES in Javascript so you can send an AES
假设你想用Javascript来实现AES，你可以发送一个AES文档给浏览器浏览器就可以自己用AES
library to the browser and have the
browser actually do AES by itself. So in
浏览器就可以自己用AES
this case what you'd like to, to is you'd
like to both shrink the code size, so that
所以，在那种情况下，你可能会缩小代码尺寸，
on the network there's minimum traffic to
send a library over to the browser but, at
好让网络有一个最小的传输，在发送文档给浏览器的时候。
the same time, you'd like the browser
performance to be as fast as possible. And
但是同时，你想让浏览器效率尽可能的快，
so this is something that we did a while
ago essentially the idea is that the code
所以有个办法我们以前就做过，就是
that actually gets send to the browser
doesn't have any pre compute table and as
代码发送给浏览器时不做任何预计算的表，
a result is fairly small code. But then
the minute it lands on the browser, what
结果就是一个非常小的代码，但当它到达浏览器时
the browser will do is actually pre
compute all the tables. So in some sense
浏览器将要做的是预计算这些表。
the code goes from just being small and
compact. It gets bloated with all these
所以，某种意义上说，代码将会小而简洁。
precomputed tables. But those are stored
on the laptop, which presumably has a lot
但在遇到预计算表时就会膨胀。这些都是储存在笔记本上的，
of memory. And then once you have the
precomputed tables you actually encrypt
并且有大量的内存。然后一旦你拥有了预计算表，你就可以用他们来加密了
using them. And that's how you get the
best performance. Okay? So if you have to
就是这样，你就可以拥有了最好的性能。
stand in implementation AES over the
network, you can kind of get the best of
所以，如果你使用网络来实现AES，你可能就是世界上最快的。
all worlds. Whereas, the code over the
network is small, but when it reaches the
无论怎样，代码通过网络时候是很小的，不过当它到达目标客户端时，
target client, it can kind of inflate
itself. And then get the best performance
它可以让它自己膨胀起来，并且在客户端处理加密的时候
as it's doing encryption on the clients.
Now AES is such a popular block cipher,
变得高效。现在AES是一套非常流行的分组密码，
now essentially when you build crypto into
products essentially your supposed to be
现在，当你需要对产品加密时，你很有可能想到使用AES，
using AES, and as a result Intel actually
put AES support into the processor itself.
并且Intel可以让处理器支持AES。
So since Westmere there are special
instructions in the Intel processor to
Westmere,自从这款特殊指令的Intel处理器问世，加快了AES的速度。
help accelerate AES. And so I listed these
instructions here. They come in two pairs,
并且我在这里列出这些产品。他们有两部分，aesenc和aesenclast,
aesenc and aesenclast. And then, there's aesekygenassist. So, let me explain
以及aesekygenassist.那么，让我来解释下他们是做什么的。
what they do. So, aesenc essentially
implements one round of AES. Namely, apply
aesenc实质上执行了一轮AES加密
the three functions in the XOR with the
round key. And aesenclast basically
也就是那三个函数和轮密钥异或的那部分。
implements the last round of AES.
Remember, the last round didn't have the
aesenclast实际上执行了AES的最后一轮。记住，最后一轮中
mix columns phase. It only had the subs
bytes and shift rows. And so that's why
是没有列混合的，只有字节代换和行移位。
the aesenclast does. And the way you
call these instructions is using 128 byte
这就是为什么aesenclast这么做。并且
registers which correspond to the states
of AES. And so you would have one register
你使用128字节的寄存器正好和AES的状态一致。
containing the states and one register
containing the current round key. And then
所以，你会用一个寄存器来存放状态，用一个寄存器来存放轮密钥。
when you call AES on these two registers,
basically, they would run one round of AES
然后，当你访问这两个寄存器上的AES时，它们将运行AES的一轮
and place the result inside of this XMM
one state register. And as a result if you
并且把结果放在一个XMM的寄存器中。并且
wanted to implement the whole AES. All you
would do is, call aesenc nine times. Then
如果你想要实现整个AES，你要做的就是调用aesenc 9次。
you would call aesenclast one time. These
ten instructions are basically the entire
然后你再调用aesenclast一次。这10个指令，基本上就是整个的AES应用
implementation of AES. That's it. It's that
easy to implement AES on this hardware
这就是为什么AES在硬件上很容易实现的原因，
and they claim because these operations
are now done inside the processor not
并且声称这些运算都只在处理器内部完成
using external instructions that are
implemented in the processor. They claim
并不使用外部指令。还声称
that they can get a fourteen X speedup
over say an implementation that's running
它们可以得到一个14倍的X加速，说在以
in the same hardware but implementing AES without these special instructions. So
同样硬件运行的AES应用没有特殊的指令。
this is quite a significant speed up and
the facts are now lots of Products that
所以，这是一个标志性的加速，并且现在已经有由特殊指令
make use of these special instructions.
And let's just say that this is not
构成的产品大量应用了。然后，让我们来说下，这并不是Intel的一个特例。
specific to Intel, if you're in
AMD and they also implemented.
假如你使用的是AMD,那么在他们的bulldozer结构里也用相似
exactly kinda similar instructions in
their bulldozer architecture and further
的指令来实现，在他们的产品或未来的产品中。
and future architectures. Okay, so let's
talk about the security of AES. I wanna
好吧，下面让我们来讨论下AES的安全性。
mention just two attacks here. Obviously,
AES has been studied quite a bit. But the
这里我想说两种攻击。显而易见，AES被研究很多了。
only two attacks on the full AES are the
following two. So, first of all, if you
不过只有两个攻击在全部AES上。就是接下来要讲的
wanted to do key recovery, the best
attack, basically, is only four times
首先，假如你想要做密钥恢复，最好的攻击，只有
faster than exhaustive search. Which mean
that instead of a hundred and. 28 bits
穷举搜索的4倍快。这就意味着
key, really you should be thinking of AES.
Is 126 bit key. Cause exhaustive search,
相当于你只用考虑126比特的AES密钥而不是128比特的。
really it's gonna four times faster than
it should. Of course due to the 126, it's
事实上，它确实是穷举搜索的4倍快，当然由于是126比特
still. More time than we have to compute,
and this really does not hurt the security
依然超过了我们的计算范围，并且这没有破坏AES的安全性。
alias. The more significant attack is,
actually, on AES-256. It turns out there's a
更有影响力的破解办法是，AES-256.
weakness in the key expansion design of
aes which allows for, what's called a
他利用了扩展密钥的一个弱点
related key attack. So, what's a related
key attack? Essentially, if you give me
叫做相关密钥攻击。什么是相关密钥攻击？
about two to the 100 input output pairs
for aes, but from four related keys. So,
假如你给我2的100次方个AES输入输出对，而且来自4个相关密钥，
these are keys that are very closely
related, namely key number one. Is just
这些密钥关系比较紧密，换句话说，K1只经过
one bit flip of key #two, which is just
one flip, bit flip of key #three, which is
一个比特的反转成为K2，K2也只经过一次反转就成为K3，
just one flip bit flip of key #four. These
are very closely related keys, if you like
再反转成为K4.这些密钥关系非常紧密，
your [inaudible] distances very short. But
if you do that, then, in fact, there is a
如果你想要你的密钥间距离很短的话。但是如果你那样做的话。
two to the 100 attack. Now you should say,
well, two to the 100 is still impractical.
事实上，有2的100次方次攻击。你可能会说2的100次方是不切实际的。
This is still more time than we can
actually run today. But nevertheless, the
然而这仍超出我们现在的计算能力。
fact that it's so much better than an
exhaustive search attack, it's so much
然而，它已经比穷举搜索好太多了，它比2的256次方好太多，
better than two to the 56, is kind of a
limitation of the cipher. But generally,
这是密码的一个限制。但是一般来说
it's not a significant limitation, because
it requires related keys. And so, in
这不是一个很有效的限制，因为它需要相关密钥。
practice, of course, you're supposed to be
choosing your keys at random, so that you
所以，实际上，你应该随机选择你的密钥，让你的密钥在系统中
have no related keys in your system. And
as a result, this attack wouldn't apply.
没有相关性。结果就会是这个攻击不奏效。
But if you do have related keys, then
there's a problem. So this is the end of
但是如果你选择的相关密钥，就会出现问题。
the segment, and in the next segment we're
gonna talk about more provably secure
那么，这一小节就要结束了，在下一节中，
constructions for block ciphers.
我们将要讨论一些在结构上可证明安全的分组密码。